let's move to system calls so how does
the operating system allow users and programs
to use an interface with the hardware and
the resources of a computer the answer to
that question is system calls there is a middle
layer which consists of all the functions
the operating system keeps for the applications
to actually communicate with
the hardware when you want to open a file
you
need to read from the disk what you do is
that let's say you double click on an icon
in your desktop when you do this at a certain
point you would need to use a function that
is actually reading the stuff from the disk
that function belongs
to the operating system which means that when
you want to read a file at a certain point
you will enter a function that belongs to
the operating system and the operating system
will take control and do the required job
which is communicate with the hardware in
this
case
the disk to read or to write to a file
when we discuss system calls we need to talk
about dual mode and multimodal operation
there's a reason why we have a system
calls in the operating system
you can think of these questions or similar
ones:
what if a program gets stuck in an infinite
loop? what if it alters the data of another
program what if it modifies the operating
system?
you see that there are a lot of things that
could happen that are potentially dangerous
so what you want is to protect the hardware
and the operating system and the other users
by having this middle layer which you need
to give control to the operating system in
order to do sensitive operations of course
here I am sort of implicitly assuming that
we have a bug free operating system
it's not a malicious operating system it's
not corrupted so we can trust the operating
system of course if this assumption does not
hold what i'm saying doesn't really make sense
but from this course let's assume that the
operating system is something that is working
correctly and that we can trust
so it turns out that when you want to talk
with the hardware/whether you are allowed
to do that or not depends on a certain bit
that it's set in a register of the hardware
this mode bit can have two values
let's assume it just has two values for now
if the value is equal to zero then
the hardware assumes you are in kernel mode
so it assumes that who is trying to communicate
with the hardware is the operating system
when the bit is set to one it assumes that
two is running the command is the user or
the application of the user so in this case
we're talking about user mode which is
the opposite to kernel mode
if you try to run up privileged instruction
so to basically do an input/output
operation with the hardware without setting
the
kernel (the mode bit to 0 without being in
kernel
mode) than the hardware will create
an interrupt
remember what I said before and it will wake
up the operating system because someone is
trying to get some information or some interaction
with the hardware without being allowed to
because
it is not the operating system this is what
that I said
is it a privileged instruction? then it can
only be executed in kernel mode. Are you running
a
user program or is the computer in this
case running a user program then you switch
the mode bit to one and then you can run
the code so that that code if it tries to
do something with the hardware that it is
not
allowed to do will cause an interrupt and
this interrupt will wake up the operating
system
in practice there are more than two modes
to think about virtual machines for example
we will discuss this in a dedicated lecture
later on
you know that if you are running I don't know
a
Windows machine inside your Ubuntu machine
in principle you can trust the Windows machine
so when the Windows machine wants to do
some interaction with the hardware despite
the fact that that is not the real operating
system attached to the hardware it's something
you can trust so you
can try to give it let's say a bit of more
power than you would give to an external application
you might not trust some system has four
multiple levels for the different privileged
instructions
you have in your hardware still the important
thing
is if you try to execute the privileged instruction
and you don't have the privilege because you
are not the kernel then an interrupt
will wake up the operating system and the
operating
system will decide what to do based on its
own code now even if you control the access
to the hardware (all hardware) through a system
call
there is still a question here
what if I run a program that never tries to
communicate with the hardware that never goes
through a system call, how do I make sure
that this will terminate? so in general can
I be sure that each program will generate
an interrupt?
the answer to that is no so what happens
is that there is specialized hardware in this
case the clock that is continuously generating
an interrupt periodically independently of
what other programs are doing and thanks
to that you know that you will always periodically
wake up the operating system with an interrupt
and when the operating system wakes up it
can then check whether everything is ok if
there
is a program that is running for too much
time and so on so this is what I just said